<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The soules lamentations, and loue to God Preces &amp; lachrymae. Dumps and teares of repentance.</title>
            <author>B. L., fl. 1614.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04962</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15104</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100180</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836031</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836031</idno>
            <idno type="VID">274</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04962)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 274)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1314:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The soules lamentations, and loue to God Preces &amp; lachrymae. Dumps and teares of repentance.</title>
                  <author>B. L., fl. 1614.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[152]+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho: Purfoot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. 1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the sinner" (leaf A4) signed: B.L.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-G¹² .</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; all after p. [152] (leaf G12) lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:274:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:274:1"/>
            <p>THE SOVLES Lamentations, and loue to God.</p>
            <q>Preces &amp; Lachrymae.</q>
            <p>Dumps and teares of REPENTANCE.</p>
            <q>Aut ora, aut abi.</q>
            <q>Aut Poenitendum, aut pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reundum.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho: Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot. An:</hi> 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:274:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:274:2"/>
            <head>To the Christian READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hinke not (good Chriſtian REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER) that theſe Prayers may on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be appropriated vnto my ſelfe. They are not onelie the Anatomie of my Soule, and the diſcouery of my life; but whatſoeuer poenitent &amp; true hearted Chriſtian ſhall light vpon them, I doubt not but he will thinke they were deuized &amp; ordained of God for him. By them thou maiſt
<pb facs="tcp:274:3"/> find the Scripture verified, which ſaith; <hi>To the weake I become as weake, that I may winne the weake,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9 22. Or rather that, <hi>Whether wee be afflicted, it is for your conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſaluation; or whether wee bee comforted, it is for your conſolation &amp; ſaluation,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.6. If God bring ſome to the gates of death for the comfort of others; what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count wee all ought to make joyntly of our ſelues, and what poſſible comfort to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter one vnto another ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, in temptations, in afflictions, in pouerties, in neceſſities, in all the worlds jniuries wherewith wee are
<pb facs="tcp:274:3"/> vexed euery day, thou ſeeſt. Seeing alſo wee eſteeme nor to diſcouer our nakedneſſe, and to ſet our jnfirmities vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the view of men for his ſervants ſakes, that their ioy may be full; knowing that if they be weake, ſo are wee, if they be ſtrong, ſo are we: if they be ſinfull, ſo are we: if they be poenitent, ſo are we. Let God be glorified, and let euery ſorrowfull ſoule tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in Chriſt vpon the view of our weaknes. For he that refuſed not vs, refuſeth none of his that come vnto him, call vpon him faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, turne from jniquity, and worſhip him in ſpirit and in
<pb facs="tcp:274:4"/> truth. This one thing I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of thee, Aske not my name: it will not profit thee; I am thy fellow ſeruant, let that ſuffice thee: In thy prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber me for a while, if thou know mee, and know me by thy ſelfe, and it ſhall ſatisfie me to the full: I doe &amp; will pray for thee. Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt be with thy Spirit. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:274:4"/>
            <head>To the Sinner.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Sinner: bee not offended at the paſſions of theſe Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Thou wilt not: thou canſt not: if euer thou haſt felt either thy ſinnes, or thy ſauiour; the one to afflict and affright thee, the other to eaſe &amp; refreſh thee. There is no greater burden then the burden of ſin: There is no greater ioy then the ioy of the holy Ghoſt, giuen and inſpired of God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, The one is hell, and the other is Heauen here on Earth. <hi>The ſpirit of a man will ſuſtaine his infirmity: but a wounded ſpirit who can beare?</hi> And ſo contrary: The hart that is poſſeſſed with <hi>The peace of God that paſſeth all vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding;</hi> no doubt, <hi>reioyceth with ioy vnſpeakeable and glorious.</hi> Adde hereunto: Jf the deare Saints of God, (eſpecially the holy Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi>) forced not, as it were, to ſhunne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelus
<pb facs="tcp:274:5"/> in the eye of the world, that they might ſatisfie their Conſciences, and glorifie God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Jt ought not to ſeeme ſtrange to any ſanctified ſoule, that the Author hereof hath made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe (in a manner) a gazing ſtocke to the world, to Angels, and to men: <hi>To become weake vnto the weake that he might winne the weake; all to all, that at the leaſt hee might gaine ſome.</hi> Jt is no matter what ſhame be poured on the face of a ſinfull, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and mortall man: ſo that one ſoule thereby may be gained to Chriſt. And J like exceedingly of that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent reſolution of ſupereminent <hi>Saint Auguſtine. Confitebor infirmitates meas oraturis pro me fratribus.</hi> Be thy diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what it will, this is mine in God. And ſo I wiſh thee the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of heart in the Sau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r of the world; of whome I am ſure thou hast great need, as well as I.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in truth and charity. <hi>B: L.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:274:5"/>
            <head>DEVOVT PRAYERS.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A Confeſſion, lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſubmiſſion to God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, my God: I haue ſinned, and done wickedly, I haue grieuouſlie ſinned, &amp; done excéeding wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly: my ſinnes are in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:274:6"/> infinite, and moſt abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in nature. Oh good Lord: I haue prouoked thine excellent Maieſtie, and thy ſtrong power, and thine vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Iuſtice, to condemne me bodie and ſoule ſodainly. Surely it is of thy mercy that I am not already co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed: I haue deſerued preſently, euen now (Lord) before the next nioment, to bée deliuered vp into the hands of hell, and of the Prince of darkneſſe, the Tyrant of the ſoule of man, Satan the Deuil. For I haue ſerued him and neglected thée: I haue from my youth obeyed him and deſpiſed thy Maieſty (oh moſt glorious, mightie,
<pb facs="tcp:274:6"/> and terrible God) thy power, and thy Iuſtice I haue deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſet at naught: And yet if this were all: I had committed but ſmall offence in reſpect of that which I haue done. For thy mercy, thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie (oh Lord) thy compaſſions (oh good God) thy compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons infinite, and vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and vnconceiuable, euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more alluring me, calling me back, &amp; eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beſéeching me (my Conſcience bearing witneſſe) to refraine from iniquitie, I haue caſt behind me, and moſt vile wretch, then whom there is none liueth more wretched that ſhall be ſaued, I haue tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and trampled vnder my
<pb facs="tcp:274:7"/> féet. True it is (my God and my mercifull Redéemer) it is moſt true: that when thou haſt offered mee grace, I haue refuſed it, &amp; when thine Angell hath ſtood on my right hand, and Satan on the left, I haue reiected thine Angell, and turned aſide vnto Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, I haue leaned vnto the left hand, and not vnto the right. So I haue traiterouſly miſuſed thy Maieſtie, &amp; haue ſhewed my ſelfe a notorious, wilfull, and vnrepentant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell: yea as a ſwift Roe of the Forreſt, or as a Dromedarie of Midian, or as a wild Aſſe of the Wildernes, that ſnuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth vp wind at pleaſure: I
<pb facs="tcp:274:7"/> haue runne haſtily and head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long from the right and high way of life, into by-paths of death and deſtruction: I haue entred league with ſins, and haue trauailed quietly hand in hand with the Princes of euerlaſting darkneſſe: I haue ſuffered my ſelfe to be led by them vnto the bottomles pit: &amp; therein I had almoſt plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged my ſelfe vnawares: I was euen cleane gone from thy preſence, and remembred thée no more: Then, euen then (oh ſweet God) when I was held in chaines of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, thou didſt ſend thine An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell and deliuer me. What ſhall I giue vnto thée? How
<pb facs="tcp:274:8"/> ſhall I be thankfull? I will praiſe thée with ioyfull lips: I will ſing to thée fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground of my heart. Accept the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of praiſe, I will take the cup of ſaluation, and pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée. Behold I come vnto thée right humbly, oh Lord heare me, oh Lord heare me: O Lord deſpiſe me not. If thou makeſt as though thou heareſt not, I die, and what profite is there in my bloud? Spare me (good Lord) ſpare me Heare and forgiue, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto thée Chriſt Ieſus, hée came into the world to ſaue ſinners: of whom not S. <hi>Paul,</hi> but I, euen I the ſlaue of ſinne that now am before
<pb facs="tcp:274:8"/> thée, I am the chiefe: which I ſpeake not (Lord) for faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but from the depth of an oppreſſed and wearied Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience thou knoweſt: It is time for thée now to lay to thy hand: for they haue deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy law within my ſoule. They, euen mine enemies, &amp; thine enemies, my ſinnes and villanies haue deſtroyed thy law. I am brought euen hard to deaths dore, and Sathan, yea truely many Sathans, and many fiends, and furies, and concupiſcences, and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of Diuels in me haue almoſt made an end of mée. My ſoule is a pray vnto them. O Lord deliuer mée, and bée
<pb facs="tcp:274:9"/> mercifull vnto me. Deliuer my ſoule from the iawes of the Lyons. Deliuer me for Ieſus Chriſts ſake, ſprinckle his bloud ouer my ſcorched Conſcience: yet if thou ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to lye a while in theſe flames, Lord grant mee pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and I willingly ſuffer. Thy will bée done. I know thou wilt deliuer me, for thou haſt promiſed and canſt not lye, and thou art able readily: For thine is the kingdome, the power, and the glorie, for euer and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:274:9"/>
               <head>¶ A wreſtling with hardnes of heart, and a betaking of the Soule vnto Gods diſpoſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H mercifull Lord God, I am vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſhamed &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded: I am grieued at the very heart: my Soule is heauie and full of ſorrow; my bones are dryed, and my ſight fayleth me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of my ſinnes. I lye in the midſt of my cruell ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the ſnares of Hell doe hold my heart in heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: it grieueth me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:274:10"/> it grieueth me very ſore, the remembrance of mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities is a vexation vnto my ſoule, the ſhame of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which yet I haue not ſhamed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit in thy ſight careleſly, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, preſumptuouſly, and péeuiſhly, doth euen aſtoniſh and amaze my wounded and languiſhing conſcience: Yet I muſt confeſſe and will not deny vnto thée (Oh my God) I haue ſinned excéedingly. Ah Lord God ſhew me thy countenance, and turne thy louing and fauourable face to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, giue eare vnto my prayers, and conſider my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations; my mournfull meditations, how I mourne
<pb facs="tcp:274:10"/> in my ſelfe, and am vexed. Héere (Oh Lord) yet vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to heare my requeſt, vouchſafe to heare the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of my ſinfull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly life, of my wanton, and wicked behauiour; of my vile and abhominable ſinnes and tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wherby I haue diſmayed my heart, daunted my courage of faith and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, &amp; euen (without thée) dammed my ſelfe body and ſoule. Heare I moſt humbly beſéech thée (moſt louing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of heauen) who neuer diſdaineſt nor ſcorneſt them that come vnto thée. Heare my ſinnes, my ſinnes, my ſinnes. Alas: how can I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peate
<pb facs="tcp:274:11"/> them? how can I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them? they are moe in number then the haires of my head, and my heart hath failed mée. I am euen already in the hell, and I lye couered with them and blinded (O God) I cannot ſée thy face. If not now, euen when thou wilt. If thou neuer wilt, I know it not, for who hath knowen thy mind (O Lord) or who hath béene thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celler? Yet ſeeing I know not whether thou wilt ſhine vnto mée in the face of Ieſus Chriſt, or no: I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore truſt in thee, and reſt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon thée, &amp; bequeath my ſoule vnto thée, though thou kill
<pb facs="tcp:274:11"/> mée. And now according to my duty I will confeſſe, if hatefull heart filled with ſin do ſay not for my duties ſake, yet for the eaſe of my ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke: and if I ſo hate my ſelfe, and enuy mine owne eaſe, yet euen for ſpite to my corrupted conſcience; I will confeſſe my wickedneſſe, and I will lay open my abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, that I may delight in their remembrance, not that I delight in them, but that I abhorre them, and my ſelfe for them, and therein I take delight. Wherefore I confeſſe vnto thine eternall Maieſtie fréelie without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, willingly without
<pb facs="tcp:274:12"/> compulſion, gladly, and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, ioyfully that ſo much grace is left vnto me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, but ſorrowfully to my ſoule, (and woe worth my ſoule that euer I haue ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, defaced, wounded it) but I confeſſe, I confeſſe, &amp; where ſhall I begin: I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe I haue ſinned againſt Heauen, and againſt thée, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Earth, &amp; againſt thée, againſt my ſelfe, and againſt thee, againſt all men, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thée, againſt the whole courſe and order of nature, and againſt thée, againſt my creation, and againſt thée, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my redemption, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thée, againſt my Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,
<pb facs="tcp:274:12"/> and againſt thée, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my Sanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, Faith, Hope, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, godlyneſſe, vertue, all grace that euer was giuen me (and it hath béene giuen in great meaſure) and againſt thée; againſt thée (Oh hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father) and thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, mercy, and glory, and power, and Iuſtice, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I haue offended and treſpaſſed moſt haynouſly &amp; villanouſly. Oh Lord par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me, Oh Lord forgiue me, forgiue my pride, and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, forgiue my neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, contempt, and ſecurity; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue my idlenes, and vanity; forgiue my prophanes, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie;
<pb facs="tcp:274:13"/> forgiue my vncleane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and vnchaſtity; forgiue my oppreſſion, &amp; iniury; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue my groſſe, and godleſſe, and ſhamefull, and vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and vnmeaſurable, and vnſatiable wickedneſſe. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept my confeſſion, accept my contrition, accept my acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, accept my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and condemnation of my ſelfe; for mine owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience hath condemned me, and my ouer-many, and out-crying ſinnes haue witneſſed againſt me, if thou (Oh mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Iudge) pronounce the ſentence of damnation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mée, it is thy mercy that thou haſt ſtaied thy fierce
<pb facs="tcp:274:13"/> wrath, &amp; ten thouſand times deſerued vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thus long: yea verily, that thou didſt not forthwith paſſe thine irreuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable ſentence, it is thy great mercie. If now thou wilt do it and ſhew mee mercy no more, thou mayeſt do it in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry equitie of Iuſtice, thou haſt my confeſſion, it doth me good that I haue béen vexed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, would it might pleaſe thée I might be more vexed vntill my hatred be perfect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vngodlineſſe; thy will be done. I commit my ſelfe into thy hands. Do with me as ſeemeth good in thine owne eies, thou art a gracious God. Death is my deſert, I am e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:274:14"/> glad and it reioyceth me, that yet in one thing I can be obedient vnto thèe, euen in yéelding my ſoule to thy holy will though it bee to throwe downe to hell. Hell is my right and my portion, the enheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance that I haue deſerued. If I be caſt thereinto I muſt bée content: But yet there is hope. I deale with a mercifull Iudge; well: let there be no hope, Take my confeſſion O God of my ſoule, do thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, if I dye I die worthie of a thouſand deaths, none more worthy. Alas my ſoule, alas my ſoule, Come ſwéet Ieſus, come quickly, the pit is déepe, it is bottomleſſe, deſpaire hath
<pb facs="tcp:274:14"/> taken hold vpon me, and it draweth me, Lord ſhall I be damned indéed? oh take the ſacrifice of a contrite ſpirit: oh remember the bloud of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: oh waſh me, and cleanſe me, and thou ſhalt find no wickedneſſe in me. Lord ſhal I be damned, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time haue truſted in thée, and haue hoped in thy holy name? I commit my ſoule into thine hands; oh remember thy ſon Chriſt; and ſo I commit it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy mercifull hands again: For thine is the kingdome, the power, and the glory, for euer and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:274:15"/>
               <head>¶ A comfortable conceit vpon review of the ſoule vnder Gods protection: And an earneſt entreatie for godly perſeuerance.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Committed my ſoule into thy hands (oh Lord thou GOD of mercie) render it, reſtore it now; nay thine it is and kéepe it I beſéech thee, and let mée haue a ſight of it. Oh thanks bée vnto thy diuine Maieſtie and vnſpeakable mercy, that yet once againe thou haſt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and cleanſed it, that thou
<pb facs="tcp:274:15"/> haſt ſprinckled the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt ouer it, that thou haſt adorned and beautified it with glorious grace, and haſt not taken thine holie Spirit from me. Lord pardon my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulnes. Goe my ſoule vnto thy God at all times, for he loueth thée, he hath once lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thée, and he loueth thée for euer. Goe vnto him, and tye thy ſelfe, be not ſeparated oh my ſoule. He is thy God, he is thy Creator, he is thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer, he is thy Sauiour. O worſhip thou him in the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of holineſſe. Oh mercifull Lord God haue pittie yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine on my diſtreſſed, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne, and forſaken ſoule. It
<pb facs="tcp:274:16"/> is wonderfully wounded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the death. Oh ſaue me, ſaue me oh Lord, why am I thus? why art thou angry with me for euer? I will hope in thy holy name, oh let me not go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way aſhamed becauſe I haue put my truſt in thée. Who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer truſted in thée, and was confounded? And ſhall I? Surely thou wilt heare mee, thou wilt helpe me, thou wilt comfort me; My heart tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth mée: thy ſpirit beareth witneſſe vnto me, that I ſhall bee relieued, and comforted, and made glad, and excéeding ioyfull, with the light of thy countenance. Behold, euen as the eyes of a ſeruant doe
<pb facs="tcp:274:16"/> looke vnto the hand of his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and the eyes of a maiden vnto the hand of her Miſtres, euen ſo mine eyes wayt vpon thée my God, vntill thou haue mercy vpon me. Make ſpéed O Lord and be not ſlack, it is time, it is high time I beſéech thee Lord let me beg my ſoule out of the hands of Satan, for Ieſus ſake, and draw my ſoule (oh louing Father) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Ieſus Chriſt: let him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Satan to yéeld it vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Seeing he hath no title, no intereſt, why ſhould hee haue any poſſeſſion, oh that it were wholy imployed in thy ſeruice. Heare then Lord, and forgiue all my ſinnes paſt, my
<pb facs="tcp:274:17"/> Roſe-coloured and bloud-red ſinnes: remember thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in Ieſus Chriſt my only Sauiour &amp; moſt louing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer; to whome with thée and the holie Ghoſt, one God Almighty, eternall, and moſt mercifull, bee praiſe, and glorie, for euer and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ An excellent wreſtling with Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H ſwéet Ieſu Chriſt ſonne of God, ſonne of the Father, lord of life, ſonne of
<pb facs="tcp:274:17"/> Dauid, redéemer of the world haue mercy vpon me miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinner. I haue defaced the glorious Image after which I was created: I haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted my wayes, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my ſoule into the power of Satan. I was held cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, and bound in the chaines of euerlaſting darkenes, yet thou (Oh Lord) didſt redéeme mée with thy moſt precious bloud: thou didſt deliuer me, and ſet me at libertie: thou diddeſt offer vp thine owne body vpon the croſſe, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thy ſelfe vnto the death for my ſake, and this my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption thou didſt ſeale in my heart by the moſt comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb facs="tcp:274:18"/> gift of Faith, and other Chriſtian vertues attending therevpon: ſo that I gaue my ſelfe to loue thée, and chéere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to ſerue thée; and call vpon thée: then didſt thou anſwere me againe, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledſt my heart with gladnes; yea (ſwéet Ieſu) thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that my heart within mée hath leaped, and daunced for ioy of thy louing cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance, and vnſpeakable mercies. May it pleaſe thee, I know it doth pleaſe thée (Oh merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Redéemer) to continue thy louing kindnes towards mée. I know, and I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe (for if I deny I am a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) that I haue notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:274:18"/> thy tender loue towards me, in redéeming my ſinfull and wretched ſoule, greatly, and notoriouſly abuſed, and contemned thy goodnes; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonly, and wickedly kicked, and ſpurned againſt thy holie grace, the ſeale of mine eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall election, and redemption, wonderfully, and ſtrangely, (oh good Chriſt) thou knoweſt moſt villanouſly, preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and almoſt deſpightful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defacing and raſing out the print thereof by moſt heinous tranſgreſſions heaped vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, &amp; encreaſing in great meaſure in moſt vile and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable ſort; ſo that I had almoſt loſt faith, and fallen
<pb facs="tcp:274:19"/> from grace: But continuall and euerlaſting praiſe bée gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to thée: thou haſt lifted me vp fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the gates of death, from the pit of hell, and power of the Diuell. The ſlye and ſubtill ſnares of damnation were ſpread vnder me, and I ſtumbled, and fell; and now was hell and death, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, preparing a triumph ouer my ſoule, now was the Diuell ſtepping with his grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy téeth to teare; and loe, thou ſonne of God, thou ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of men, thou ſtrong and mighty by thy mighty power, whereby thou art able to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due all things vnto thy ſelfe, didſt pluck me out of his téeth,
<pb facs="tcp:274:19"/> and deliuer me. What ſhall I render vnto thy Maieſtie? thy power, thy goodneſſe, thy mercie, thy moſt vndeſerued (true Lord, and moſt true) compaſſion, and pittie? What ſhall I render vnto thée for all the good that thou haſt done vnto me? Surely I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe vnto thée my wickednes, and be ſorrie for my ſinne. I will magnifie and praiſe thy name for euer. I will ſpeake of thy louing kindneſſe, and make mention of thy ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Oh Lord, who is like vnto thée, that deliuereſt me from him that is to ſtrong for mée, and ſpoileth mee? My ſoule ſhall make her boaſt of
<pb facs="tcp:274:20"/> thée, and ſhal not be aſhamed, becauſe thou Lord haſt holpen me, and comforted me. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer (oh my Ieſus) I will not ceaſe to pray vnto thee, diſpoſe me therevnto I moſt humbly beſéech thée, for without thée I can doe nothing. Oh let my prayer come before thée, and enter into thy preſence, Let me neuer be ſo mightily ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and ſo ſhamefully ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne as I haue béene. Giue me thy conſtant ſpirit: bréed in my heart and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence a deadly hatred, and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate enmity of ſinne and wickedneſſe: let me neuer be reconciled vnto them againe: Oh let my ſoule loue thy moſt
<pb facs="tcp:274:20"/> precious blood, by which it is waſhed and cleanſed from moſt vile corruptions. Let me die (oh Lord) and depart this life before I ſo contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly, as indeede I haue done, tread, and trample it, as it were vnder my profane féet. Oh let me die firſt I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly deſire thée (my ſwéet Sauiour:) For why ſhould I liue to diſhonour thée in ſuch ſort? Why ſhould I liue ſtill to prouoke thy wrath, and mine owne vnquietneſſe? I haue profaned thy ſanctified and ſanctifying blood, I haue buffeted thée on the face; I haue whipped and ſcourged thée moſt cruelly: I haue by
<pb facs="tcp:274:21"/> moſt odious impiety crucified thée afreſh vnto my ſelfe. Ah ſinnefull wretch laden with iniquity; heauie laden; Oh laden, oh when wilt thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh me? quicken me in thy righteouſneſſe, and clenſe me from all my filthineſſe, oh clenſe me &amp; I ſhall be cleane, whiter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſnow, clearer then glaſſe, acceptable to the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Iudge God our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, louing, and mercifull, who neuer refuſeth thée (oh Chriſt) his welbeloued Son. I beſeech thée, I beſeech thée reſtore mee; make glad my heart againe, render now thy grace, which I haue loſt by my treſpaſſe; and from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous
<pb facs="tcp:274:21"/> ſinnes (oh Lord) keepe me: ſet Angells about me to draw me by violence from ſuch vngodlineſſe. If thou wilt thou canſt make me cleane, and thou art mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy it ſelfe, and yet hitherto none hath truſted in thée, and béen ſent away empty, and thou art able, For all power is giuen to thée in heauen and in earth; and at the name of Ieſus euery knée muſt bow, both of things in heauen, and things in earth, and things vnder the earth: now I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my cauſe vnto thy diuine wiſedome, and vnſpeakable mercy: now I craue pardon, now I craue grace, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance
<pb facs="tcp:274:22"/> therein, and in thy good time thou wilt not fayle to giue, (oh Lord) ſtrengthen my patience, and increaſe my faith, for thine is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the power, and the glorie, for euer and euer <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A comfortable confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Supplication.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, great and fearfull, moſt mighty, and full of ſtrength: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how I mourne in my prayer, and am vexed, my
<pb facs="tcp:274:22"/> ſorrowes are gone ouer my head, my ſinnes are bound vp in a bundle to be layd vppon mée, nay to be repeated, my ſoule is payned and pined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way through my dayly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainyng, and yet thou (oh righteous Iudge) continueſt holy, and iuſt in thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Thy puniſhments are inflicted vpon me; thine arrowes ſticke faſt in mée, thou haſt wounded me ſore; but in mercy thou haſt chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me, my rebellious haue deſerued much more, nay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite; and yet it pleaſeth thy Maieſtie to be mercifull vnto me, euen ſo Father becauſe it is thy good pleaſure to ſaue
<pb facs="tcp:274:23"/> ſinners, of whom I am the chiefe. O God of mercies and compaſſions; of Father, and Spirit of all comfort, and conſolation, heare thy ſeruant that putteth his truſt in thee; heare, and giue eare: thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies haue drawne me vnto thée, and thine innumerable compaſſions haue conſtrained me to acknowledge vnto thée Holy, holy, holy, true in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; faithfull in mercy; full of kindnes, long ſuffering and of great goodnes, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull in pity, and moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull, thou ſpareſt when we deſerue puniſhment, and in thy puniſhment thou art not cruell, but ſeuere; nay rather
<pb facs="tcp:274:23"/> gentle, and mercifull: euen gentlenes, and mercy, and méekenes, and patience, and tender loue, and kindnes it ſelfe. I ſee it, I find it, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it, I giue thanks for it. What ſhall I render to thée? I will thanke thée, for thou haſt wounded, and thou haſt cured, and thou haſt healed me, thou haſt ſuffered me to ſlip into the gates of hell, and thou haſt deliuered me. Oh ye that feare the Lord, magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ye the lord with me, oh let vs come before him in the beautie of holineſſe; for hee hath regarded the contemned eſtate of a ſinner, and he one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgaue my ſinne: my ſoule
<pb facs="tcp:274:24"/> doth teſtifie &amp; make her boaſt of the Lord, I ſought him early and late, in the day time and in the night ſeaſon (this was my dutie, this was my neceſſity:) for a while he hid his face from me, and I was troubled; for a while he was angrie, and I conſumed; for a while he held my ſins before me, and I was amazed, aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and confounded: but he turned his mercie toward me, and I receiued comfort, I conceiued hope, I perceiued that of very faithfulneſſe hee cauſed me to ſuffer griefe; O magnifie the Lord with mee. He woundeth, and maketh whole againe; he afflicteth,
<pb facs="tcp:274:24"/> and he deliuereth out of afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; he hath ſhewed me ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, and yet in the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the ſorrowes that I had in my heart, his comforts haue refreſhed my ſoule. What comforts? Chriſt my Redeemer: my Sauiour, my King, and my God. Verily a King. Hee hath taken my ſins, my preſumptuous ſins, and defaced them. Hee hath entred into my ſoule, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed Satan, Legions of Deuils hee hath chaſed, and gotten himſelfe the victorie. Reioyce in the Lord thy King (oh my ſoule) he ruleth in the midſt among thine enemies. They are brought to nothing
<pb facs="tcp:274:25"/> that ſought to deſtroy thée. Ieſus is in the midſt of thée, euen in thy heart, and in thy ſoule to ſaue, he ſitteth there, euen there alſo in thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Oh my redéemed ſoule betwéene the Cherubins; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy king, behold, and be glad, his traine is with him, his Angels miniſter vnto him, &amp; about thee they ſtand to driue away the fiends of hell, and to defend thée. Why then art thou ſo ſad oh my ſoule? what aileth thée? Canſt thou not reſt vpon thy ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, thy horne, and thy buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, and the ſtrong God of thy ſaluation? O put thy truſt in God; be ſtrong, and of a good
<pb facs="tcp:274:25"/> courage, and he ſhall eſtabliſh thy heart, euen Ieſus that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth thée from the wrath to come, hee ſhall ſo eſtabliſh thine heart, and ſaue thée. O bleſſe his holie name. Oh praiſe him, and magnifie him for euer, he onely is the Lord, he onlie is the King, and there is none but he; Oh Ieſu I adore and worſhip thée. Oh Chriſt I praiſe, &amp; giue thanks vnto thée, Oh Redéemer I confeſſe vnto thée, mine is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhame, thine is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorie, mine is the weaknes, thine is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, the kingdome, the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and rule ouer ſinne and Satan, death, and hell. Sit ſtill while thou art there; be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hold
<pb facs="tcp:274:26"/> I ſcorne at ſin and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, they cannot enter. Auant Satan. Ieſus is the Lord, thou hadſt miſerablie ſpoiled me; but loe my Redeemer is come; Auant Satan. Swéet Ieſu; mightie Lord; my king; thy mercie is ſwéet, thy might is inuincible, the ſcepter of thy kingdome is a ſcepter of holineſſe; holineſſe the life of the ſoule, the ſeale of life, the earneſt of inheritance in the kingdome of Heauen. O King in my heart ſit ſtill, rule ſtill, liue ſtill. And of a truth will God dwell with man? I thanke thée, I honour thée, I adore thée. Oh King liue for euer. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:274:26"/>
               <head>¶ A verie devout and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous complaint againſt Inconſtancy &amp; Hyppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Said I would forſake my wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie in thy ſight, I reſolued from a perfect and vpright heart (oh my GOD thou knoweſt) to giue an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting farewell to my ſinne, I promiſed thy moſt ſacred and excellent Maieſtie from the ground of my grieued Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that I would neuer
<pb facs="tcp:274:27"/> returne as a Dog to my vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, or a Sow that is waſhed to the wallowing in the myre. But alas how weake? how faithleſſe? how inconſtant? how forgetfull am I? how ſoone am I caried aſide, and turned out of the way? how is my ſoule become a ſnare to take my ſelfe? how is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy a verie bondſlaue to the ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy deſires of my ſoule? how am I altogether corrupt and abhominable as before? I hate my ſinne, and I commit my ſinne, I abhorre my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and yet yéeld to my rebellion. How is my ſoule pained, and my bodie pined by reaſon of my ſinne? I haue
<pb facs="tcp:274:27"/> faſted, and watched, and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and wept, and confeſſed, and craued pardon many times, carefullie, zealouſlie, vehementlie: and haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued comfort, conceiued hope of thy conſtant ſpirit, and yet my ſinne remaineth. O vile wretch! O ſlaue of ſinne! O drudge of tranſgreſſion! O vaſſall of Satan that I am! what ſhall I doe? whither ſhall I flie? to whome ſhall I reſort for deliuerance? If I ſay vnto my bodie doe not yéeld, it reſiſteth; If I ſay to my ſoule be not ouercome, it denieth. I am wholie euill, and there is no good thing in me. And yet my ſoule is more
<pb facs="tcp:274:28"/> abhominable then this: for it flattereth me as though it would be obedient to thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (oh God) but it diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bleth with me. It is a very hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, in nothing conſtant, in nothing ſtedfaſt but in hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, and in deceipt, it promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and it performeth not. Why art thou ſo wicked oh my ſoule? why art thou ſo falſe vnto me? why doſt thou ſuffer Satan thine enemie &amp; murderer to poyſon thée, and ſo to kill thée? Oh miſerable ſoule? why wilt thou dye? oh Ieſus my life why am I departed from thée? Oh Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus come vnto me whom my ſoule loueth. One depth cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb facs="tcp:274:28"/> another: the depth of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, the depth of mercy. My miſery is déepe, but thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is bottomleſſe, &amp; I know no end therof. What then? be of good cheere my ſoule, go, ſeeke thy ſauiour, follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him. Thy ſinnes are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and thou canſt not num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them, they are heynous, and odious, and thou canſt not eſteeme the abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them: but he hath num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred them, and he knoweth their quality, and his mercies are without number &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Infinite and not defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite to any perſons; thou art not excepted; to any times this day thou ſhalt be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="tcp:274:29"/> as it is written. <hi>At what time ſoeuer, &amp;c.</hi> oh put thy truſt in God, and in the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the moſt high, thou ſhalt not miſcarry, he is the helpe of thy countenance, and thy God. Truſt to him, reſt in him, depend vpon him; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after him, wreſtle with him, pray vnto him, and leaue him not till hee beſtow a bleſſing: till he change thy heart, and make it new, be not faint, neither forgetfull; without him thou ſhalt haue no reſt, and in him thou ſhalt find reſt, and eaſe, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and ioy, and eternall life, and euerlaſting felicitie, thou knoweſt my Soule when
<pb facs="tcp:274:29"/> thou art with him thou art quiet, and glad becauſe of the light of his countenance, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou art from him, thou art ſad becauſe thou art from thy ioy. Oh ſéeke thy Redéemer; forget not thy Sauiour, his mercie is thy life, oh life grant mercie. Oh Chriſt ſaue. I am a Leaper, if thou wilt thou canſt make me cleane. I am the Publican, oh Lord bee mercifull vnto me a ſinner, a great ſinner, a grieuous ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, the chiefe of ſinners. Truth, oh truth, oh faithfull and true, oh ſwéet Ieſu, who hath néed of thy mercie as I haue? Thou canſt not beſtow it on a more néedy begger?
<pb facs="tcp:274:30"/> One drop of thy mercie ſwéet Ieſu, ſweet Ieſu. <hi>Amen, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ The dumpe or dampe of deſpaire: whereout the ſinner labouring, pittiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly complaineth and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto Chriſt Ieſus to be refreſhed and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ay by day haue I cryed vnto the Lord, and in the night when I was waking I thought vpon his mercies, and called for them. For I ſaw the vglie
<pb facs="tcp:274:30"/> ſhape and innumerable mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of my ſinnes crying vengeance day and night. I perceiued I was afflicted, my ſoule was heauie, and my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die pined away, I cheriſhed my fleſh, and it would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, it rotted, and decayed. For the anger of the Lord, &amp; the indignation of the moſt high, I brought my life down vnto the ground, and my ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows were encreaſed in my heart. For I was pained within me, and ſtraightned in my owne bowels, then ſpake I to the Almighty, and ſayd as the Prophet taught me. <hi>When thou with rebukes doeſt chaſten man for ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:274:31"/> thou makeſt his beautie to conſume away as it were a moath fretting a garment,</hi> &amp; I ſaid, <hi>My wounds ſtincke, and are corrupt through my fooliſhnes,</hi> and I ſaid, <hi>Thine arrowes ſticke faſt in me, and thy hand preſſeth mee ſore.</hi> For I prayed daily, and yet my ſinne remained, and the puniſhment of my ſinne was hard vpon me. The Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie had couered his face with glorie, and I was troubled, I found no reſt in my ſelfe, no refuge in any creature. Then I ſtood amazed in the preſence of my God. For I could not ſpeake, my ſinnes were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded, and layed open in his
<pb facs="tcp:274:31"/> ſight, &amp; he remembred them. So I drew néerer and néerer vnto the pit, and accompted my ſelfe among the wicked. I was ſilent before the high Maieſtie and moſt excellent glorie, for I could not ſpeake, yea, my heart wandred too and fro, and I ſought to hide me from his preſence: But it would not be. The eye of iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louzie ſéeth all things, and the eare of iealouzie heareth all things, and my ſinnes were bound vp in a bundle before him, and the puniſhment for them lay ſore vpon me. Then I ſaid againe. Lord doeſt thou ſo correct thine own children? Where ſhall the wicked ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare?
<pb facs="tcp:274:32"/> Surely they ſhall va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away like ſmoake when thou appeareſt to them in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. But I ſaid of my ſelfe I am caſt out of thy preſence, and I am numbred with the reprobate generation. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, when I ſaw I could not lie hid, neither could auoid the righteouſneſſe of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Iudge, neither yet was able to pacifie my vexed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, becauſe I found no meanes in my ſelfe to forſake mine owne iniquitie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I am cloathed as with a cloake. When I perceiued indéed, and knew throughly the moſt poore, wretched, and miſerable eſtate of my ſoule,
<pb facs="tcp:274:32"/> inclinable to no goodnes, but moſt vehemently with might and maine ſtriuing againſt it: I came trembling vnto the Lord Ieſus, I made my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint and powred out my ſupplication before him, in this manner. Oh Ieſu Chriſt the onlie Sauiour, annointed of the high God: Lord of life, of conſolation, and eternitie, Redéemer of the world, recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciler of man vnto God: prieſt, and mediatour for euer, cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with the fleſh of man to deliuer man from hell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath. Oh mercie, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and compaſſion it ſelfe, thou makeſt friendſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene life and death, morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,
<pb facs="tcp:274:33"/> and immortality, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and incorruption; Heare me (O Lord) and caſt me not away: wherefore didſt thou die, but for ſinners? why didſt thou come into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world but to ſaue ſinners? To what purpoſe didſt thou deliuer thy ſelfe into the hands of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? Was not this the cauſe of thy obedient life, and cruell death, the wretchednes of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? Why then (oh Ieſu) I am a ſinner. Why art thou abſent from me? Thou camſt not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance; call me then vnto thée, and draw me: For I cannot come of my ſelfe, I cannot come when
<pb facs="tcp:274:33"/> I am called, except I bee drawen; without thée I can doe nothing: I cannot come vnto thée, Call me, draw me, come for me. I lie in the pit, I am ſpoyled of robbers: I am robbed of thy robes, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, and ſanctification. The ſpoilers are my ſinnes, my concupiſcences, my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions within me. They (oh Ieſu) euen they haue ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led mee, diſ-robed me of thy graces, disfurniſhed mee of thy riches, and vertues; Oh good Samaritan while I am weltring in my bloud, Oh while I am in my bloud, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe me not, paſſe not by me, haue pittie, and compaſſion
<pb facs="tcp:274:34"/> vpon me. Bring thy bloud, thy moſt precious bloud, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, becauſe not to be valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at any price, better then the balme of Gilead, powre it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my wounds, it is wine, it is oyle, it hath a ſauing ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, O ſaue me my Sauiour, Ieſu the ſonne of <hi>Dauid</hi> haue mercy vpon mee, I thirſt for thée, I long for thée, I faint for thée. Ieſu thou ſonne of <hi>Dauid</hi> haue mercie vpon me, I haue hoped in thy holie name. For why art thou the ſonne of <hi>Dauid?</hi> Is it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of thy ſure mercies to <hi>Dauid?</hi> and to his ſeed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer? And who is the ſéed of <hi>Dauid?</hi> are not they that call
<pb facs="tcp:274:34"/> vpon thée, that reſt in thée, that haue no other ſaluation but thée, the ſéed of <hi>Dauid?</hi> O then I haue no helper, no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, no redéemer, but thée, (oh Lord of life. O Prince of peace, oh GOD my righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.) I haue none but thée. I am then the ſeed of <hi>Dauid,</hi> performe to me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy things of <hi>Dauid,</hi> the promiſes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life. O ſonne of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> haue mercie vpon me. If thou wilt, thou canſt make me cleane, purge me oh Phyſition of the ſoule: purge mee, and make mee cleane, let thy blood waſh mee throughly, and I ſhall be cleane; I haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thy iuſt conceiued fury: no
<pb facs="tcp:274:35"/> reaſon thou ſhouldſt heare &amp; ſaue, but thine owne mercy, &amp; thine own loue: I appeale vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: wherefore haſt thou called me, and taught me thy truth? In vain? O let it not be in vaine. Wherefore do I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue thée to be ſauiour of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? in vaine? O let it not be in vain But if I be not ſaued I belieue in vaine. Lord heare my praier, and let my ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſighing come before thée. So I truſt. I will not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt, Helpe my vnbeliefe: I will lay my ſaluation on thy ſhoulders, oh Chriſt Ieſu. For thine is the kingdome, the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and the glory, for euer, and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:274:35"/>
               <head>¶ An humble ſuite for a liuely fayth.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H Almighty God, and moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Father, thou knoweſt my ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, and my rowling re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentances within me; how I am grieued, and vexed that I haue tranſgreſſed againſt thée, oh Lord thou knoweſt. The terrors, and troubles of my heart are all open before thy Maieſtie, whom that I haue prouoked to take ſwift vengeance vppon me I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, yea (oh mighty Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narche
<pb facs="tcp:274:36"/> of heauen and earth) I confeſſe freely and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that damnation of body and ſoule is my due, and the rather for that by mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities beſt knowen vnto thy ſacred Maieſtie, I haue refuſed Faith in the blood of thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt. I haue hardned my heart, and encreaſed my contempt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. Now Lord, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it hath pleaſed thée to call to my remembrance, and conſideration my tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to giue me grace to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and acknowledge them in a deteſtation of them: to ſeeke and ſue for thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt in whom thou
<pb facs="tcp:274:36"/> art well pleaſed, I beſeech thée (oh Father) good Father as thou haſt loued mankind fréely; ſo giue me the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and comfortable gift of Faith, in the death and paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, that I may beleeue ſtedfaſtly to my comfort in him, that he is the Sauiour, &amp; Redeemer; not onely of others but of me alſo, euen of me (oh Father) thy Creature, though miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably deformed by ſinne. Oh ſend thy holy ſpirit of grace into my heart, that I beeing dead &amp; ſtinking in the graue of my wickedneſſe; yet may ariſe, and liue to thée, and thy glory for euer, through
<pb facs="tcp:274:37"/> the powerfull might of Ieſus Chriſt, by an vnfained and ſetled faith in my heart. Oh heauenly Father, I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſwallowed vp of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, thy puniſhment doth ſo amaze me; Oh deliuer my ſoule from that fearfull mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. I am aſhamed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded before thee, my ſins are ſo many ſince my youth vp, &amp; now thou calleſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thy remembrance, and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not anſwere one for a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand. I will therefore lay mine hand vpon my mouth, and kéepe ſilence before thée, wayting for thy deliuerance, and for faith in Ieſus Chriſt; oh ſend me faith, liuely and
<pb facs="tcp:274:37"/> working, and comforting, that I may goe forward cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly in the path of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication all my life long. Grant this oh Father, that I may glorifie thy name, and reioyce in thée and in thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing health Ieſus Chriſt my onely Lord, Redéemer and Sauiour. To whom with thée, and that deſired and lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for holy Ghoſt, thrée per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and one Coequall, and Coeternall God, be all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and praiſe, and Dominion and Maieſtie, and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing from henceforth, and for euermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:274:38"/>
               <head>¶ A gladſome thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for the taſt of Gods mercie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ternall GOD, whoſe habitation is in heauen, and whoſe wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull and gratious prouidence in all the world: thanks be giuen to thy moſt ſacred Maieſtie, that being ſo high, thou haſt reſpect vnto the lowly: that being ſo powerfull and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, thou haſt regard to my miſery. Oh gratious and moſt louing Father in Ieſus Chriſt my Sauiour, hath it
<pb facs="tcp:274:38"/> pleaſed thee indéed to take the prey from the mighty (my ſoule from Satan) and to let the iuſt captiuitie goe frée? my ſinnefull ſoule and body in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déed, and truth, ſnared and captiued of the Prince of darknes, to be looſed from the chaines of hell, infirmitie, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normity, preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, cuſtome of iniquitie? it is true, it hath pleaſed thée? euen ſo Father, becauſe it was thy good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. I acknowledge, and confeſſe that this hath procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of thine euerlaſting and neuer dying mercies. I will therefore take vp the cup of ſaluation, that thou haſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto me, and drinke it
<pb facs="tcp:274:39"/> vp, health vnto my bones, to my bowels, to my nauill, to my ſoule. I haue ſucked the dregs of the cup of trembling; but the cup of trembling is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from me, now thou haſt refreſhed me with chéerefull wine, the bloud of Ieſus Chriſt. I will make menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy righteouſneſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, I will ſing praiſe &amp; honour vnto thée with my whole heart: I was dead, but I am aliue, I was wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered like haye; but now I ſhall flouriſh as a gréen hearb, beyond all hope. Loe: this this is the portion of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that turne from iniquity in <hi>Iacob,</hi> and feare the Lord ſeruing
<pb facs="tcp:274:39"/> him in vprightnes and truth. Thus is the Lord mercifull vnto his ſeruants whome he hath choſen: He kéepeth them that they do not fall for euer. Thus is hee mercifull vnto them for his owne ſake. O King of Kings, thou dweller in eternitie, ſéeing ſo farre it hath pleaſed thée to viſite the diſtreſſed eſtate of a ſinner, and to lead me in the path of righteouſneſſe, thou art vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable, one and the ſame, and haſt neuer vſed to repent thée of thy compaſſions, heare me, and giue eare, and looke vpon mee through thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, and pleaſe thy ſelfe with me. Grant that I
<pb facs="tcp:274:40"/> béeing continually couered with his obedience (as with a cloake) may be euer accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in thy ſight, accompanie me the whole race of my mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall life, with his, and thy moſt ſacred and wiſe grace, that ſo it may appeare to the ioye of my ſorrowfull heart, and peace of my conſcience; as alſo to the ſight and perfect knowledge of men, that thou art mercifull vnto mee of a truth, that thou haſt lifted me vp; that in thy wrath thou didſt puniſh me: but in thy mercy haſt compaſſion on me; becauſe I haue hoped in thy holy name, and haue waited for thy ſaluation. And as for
<pb facs="tcp:274:40"/> me (my God) performe the worke of comfort, which thou haſt begunne in mee, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the ioy of my ſpirit from day to day, and bring me forth into the light, a mirrour of thy mercies, &amp; a ſpectacle of thine vnſpeakable and rich com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and only Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:274:41"/>
               <head>¶ The Sinners deniall of himſelfe, and lowlie peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to bee accepted of God, and receiued into his conduct.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Almightie God, Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and God of all conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: I haue now ſéene, and had experience in déed and truth, that in me, that is in my fleſh, there dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth no good thing. For the very fountaine is corrupted, euen my heart within me, the fountaine of all my actions. I
<pb facs="tcp:274:41"/> find it indéed full of filthineſſe in it ſelfe: full of rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thée; hating thy moſt excellent Maieſtie, and euen wiſhing that thou wereſt no God at all, that it might the more francklie, and fréely ſet on fire the whole courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in me, and ſo draw me body and ſoule into the lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone, Fier that neuer goeth out. I doe heere ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fréely acknowledge and confeſſe, that my deſtruction is ſought mightily &amp; mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by my ſelfe: but my Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation is of thée. I doe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly repent me of my wicked heart, and as héereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:274:42"/> I haue in vprightnes &amp; truth dedicated and deuoted the ſame vnto thy heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly protection: (as thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt): ſo now in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner I wholy reſigne my ſelfe into thy hands, beſéeching thée to take this vngodly heart, and frame it anew, to make it pliable, and fit for thy ſelfe. I know thou haſt no néed of my ſeruice, for thou canſt command the ſtones, and they will ariſe and prayſe thée. But yet ſeeing I who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny my ſelfe, and betake my life to the good gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt my bleſſed Sauiour: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thée, oh Lord I beſeech
<pb facs="tcp:274:42"/> thée accept the ſoule of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. Let me now ſée and experience y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of Chriſt againſt Satan. I haue expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced mine owne power which is weakneſſe, not able to encounter with the ſtrong man. The life that héereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I ſhall liue, let me liue it wholy, (oh mercifull Father) by the faith in the death of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and let Chriſt liue in me by his gracious and ſanctifying ſpirit, that from henceforth I may vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly deteſt, and abhorre my former wickednes and may be renewed as a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and receiue the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt in my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:274:43"/> as a Child, euen ſo (Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of heauen): ſo be it. For thou haſt magnified thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in me, and ſo magnifie them for euer. Thou haſt diſappointed Satan of my ſoule, and ſo diſappoint him ſtill; of a truth I perceiue that thou art faithfull, and true in thy promiſes, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt thy Children with an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting loue. Glory, and honour, and great worſhip, and all power, might, and Maieſtie, be aſcribed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée. For thou art worthy oh GOD moſt high. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:274:43"/>
               <head>¶ In the inſtant and vrgent aſſault of Temptation, a very earneſt prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord, why abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt thou thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant? why hideſt thou thy face fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me? Heare thou in heauen, thy dwelling place, thou poſſeſſor of heauen and earth, thou maker of all things, thou louer of men, thou ſauer of ſoules heare and giue eare, and let my prayer enter into thy preſence. The tempter is ready, my heart is weake,
<pb facs="tcp:274:44"/> my ſoule is wicked. I ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpire againſt thee with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I ſhal enter a league with death and hell: I am fettered in the chaines of eternall damnation: Oh Lord God Almighty, ſtrong, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, heare thou in heauen thy dwelling place: Behold mine owne deſires are confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate againſt me, and mine inward affections conſpire to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to ouerthrow mee. Now euen now, am I ready to be taken away: now my ſinful body vexeth my ſimple ſoule, now my ſimple ſoule enthralleth her ſelfe to my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full body: Now heare, and helpe, oh God of heauen: my
<pb facs="tcp:274:44"/> Sauiour ſayd it; I ſurely find it: <hi>The ſpirit is willing, but the fleſh is weake.</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan is ſtrong, hee is very ſtrong, he hath ſtrengthened mee againſt my ſelfe. Oh ſtrength of Iſrael, ſtrength of thy Choſen, ſtrength of thy Children, ſtrengthen me for my ſelfe, as Satan hath ſtrengthened me againſt my ſelfe. If thou my God, my rocke, my refuge will ſaue, who can deſtroy? If thou wilt deliuer, who ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon? If thou wilt but ſay the word: let the iuſt capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie goe frée: giue mee the ſoule (oh Satan) that I haue loued for euer, that I haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected
<pb facs="tcp:274:45"/> before the world; that my ſonne hath redéemed with his precious bloud: what Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan? What ſinne? What death? What hell? What hatred? what curſe? what law? what guilty conſcience? what deſpaire? what damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can hold it backe? Thou art Almighty, thou art All-ſufficient, mighty againſt all that reſiſt thy might, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all theſe: ſufficient for all that band themſelues againſt thy ſufficiency, and therefore for theſe. For theſe (O Lord God moſt mercifull and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Father) whether they be in mee, or about mee, thou art Almighty, thou art all-ſufficient.
<pb facs="tcp:274:45"/> Wicked ſinne, a guiltie conſcience, a deſpairing ſoule, theſe are within me; O God diſpoſſeſſe them. Lawe, and curſe, hatred, and hell, death, and diuell, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation it ſelfe; theſe are about me: Oh Lord diſperſe them. Ariſe (Lord) and let thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies be ſcattered: let theſe that hate thée flée before thée. Oh deliuerer of the captiues, helper of the afflicted, relieuer of the oppreſſed, comforter of the grieued, my temptation is at hand, my temptation is at hand. I fall, I fall, Lord lift me vp. Lord lift vp the light of thy countenance vpon me. Where art thou my God? Oh
<pb facs="tcp:274:46"/> my ſoule what doeſt thou? where art thou my God? My ſoule whither wilt thou? what haue I done vnto thee? why doeſt thou betray me? But where art thou my God? Oh heare me now I call. O helpe me now I cry vnto thée. The aſſault is grieuous, the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence is villanous, the danger is deſperate, oh wretched cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature that I am: Who ſhall deliuer me from this body of death? Oh I am weake hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. I am ſoule ſicke. I am faint ſpirited. I finde no meanes of reſiſtance. Now I fall, now I yéeld, now I am tempted, now I am ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, now I conſent, now I
<pb facs="tcp:274:46"/> runne headlong vpon mine owne damnation. Oh my breaſt is pinched, my heart is pained, my ſoule afflicted, my infirmitie ſurprized, my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience vexed, mine affection enflamed, my preſumption encreaſed, I yéeld, I fall, I ſinne, I dye. Oh God, oh good God, oh gracious God heare me: oh ſpirit, oh holy ſpirit, oh comfortable ſpirit (thy name is the comforter) oh come and aſſiſt me. O Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, ſweet Ieſu, Ieſu that deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereſt vs from the wrath to come. Come heare me, come helpe me, come ſaue me, come ſtand by me. Rebuke Satan, rebuke ſinne, I beſéech thee
<pb facs="tcp:274:47"/> (my Sauiour, my gentle Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour) rebuke my ſinfull ſoule that reſteth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thée, reforme my ſoule that longeth for thée: Suffer mee not to bée tempted aboue my ſtrength, of my ſelf I haue no ſtrength; Bee thou my ſtrength, my caſtle and deliuerer, at this time, and at all times, in my perplexities, aſſaults, and temptations: So be it, euen ſo bee it, ſo I truſt, and ſo I reſt. Ieſu that deliuereſt vs from the wrath to come. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:274:47"/>
               <head>¶ A prayer for grace and diligence to pray.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H moſt mercifull God, and louing Father: I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my negligent and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe behauiour towards thée, as in all the courſe of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo chiefly in deuotion and godly praier. Haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vpon me, and forgiue my ſecuritie. I haue hindred ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good things from my ſelfe that I haue not prayed for. I haue thereby vilified thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly bleſſings, and riches of
<pb facs="tcp:274:48"/> thy mercie: I haue brought leaueneſſe vnto my ſoule: Oh gracious God, ſtirre vp my dull and dead ſpirit, and quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me in thy holineſſe, that my breaſt being ſet on fire, and enflamed with thy mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold mercies and graces, I may diligently direct my peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vnto thée, and ſo obtaine according to my neceſſitty. Open mine eies O Lord, that I may ſée my wants clearly, touch my heart that I may pray vnto thee faithfully, fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uently, &amp; continually. Heare me (oh good God) and quicken me according to thy mercie. Oh diſperſe mine iniquities as a cloud after a great raine.
<pb facs="tcp:274:48"/> Now after the time that thou haſt viſited my ſinne vpon me, returne, returne I beſéech thée in great compaſſion. My ſoule is afraid of thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I am beaten backe with feare of thy wrath; when I thinke to pray, my heart is cold within me, I am aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſodainly caſt downe. LORD, lift me vp to thy throne in prayer, thou that haſt lift me vp from the gates of death. Where is thy liuely ſpirit? Swéet God, Ieſus my Sauiour promiſed me the comfortable ſpirit. In his name I beſéech thée ſend it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my heart. It will teach me and warne me to pray: ſo ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:274:49"/> I be ſure to obtaine my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Heare me (O Lord) for my Sauiour Ieſus ſake, to whome with thée, and the holie Ghoſt be all honor, glorie, and praiſe. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A thankfull acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of diuine mercies in Iudgements.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H moſt mightie Lord God, Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, Gouernour, and poſſeſſour of Heauen and earth: Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is about thy throne, and thy kingdome is eſtabliſhed
<pb facs="tcp:274:49"/> in iudgement. Whatſoeuer pleaſeth thee, that doſt thou in heauen and in earth, and in all déepe places. Thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeſt, and conſidereſt the waies of men: and thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeſt euery man according to his workes. Thou calleſt for puniſhment, and it run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth like the ſwift lightning vpon the tranſgreſſors. Thou commandeſt vengeance, and vengeance entreth into all places, the ſtately pallaces of Princes, and the beggarly cottages of the poore. There is nothing hid fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy preſence. Thine eyes in euery place (a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times brighter then the
<pb facs="tcp:274:50"/> Sunne) behold the euill and the good. There is nothing can be deliuered from the fircenes of thy wrath. It burneth like fire euen to the bottome of hell. Thou doſt correct the wicked with the vengeance of eternall fire. Thou doſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten thine own children (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they goe aſtray and wander in the pathes of the vngodly) with the corrections of men, Infamy, pouerty, ſickneſſe of bodie, weaknes of mind, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, baniſhment, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, and temporall death. Oh Lord our gouernour how excellent is thy name? how woonderfull are thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in all the world? And
<pb facs="tcp:274:50"/> yet for all this how few there are, euen a very few, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thy worke that is done vnder the Sunne; that pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy iudgements though they be vpon themſelues? Oh palpable blindneſſe, oh dull forgetfulnes, oh great ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, oh groſſe impietie, thou ſmiteſt, and no man regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, thou puniſheſt, and no man conſidereth, thou layeſt thy iudgements to the view of all men, and no man layeth them vnto his heart. Bleſſed is hee whome thou inſtructeſt by puniſhment, and guideſt in the way of iudgement. Surely this is a great mercy, and it paſſeth all thy workes,
<pb facs="tcp:274:51"/> O teach me thy iudgements, thy louing corrections haue made me glad: To me thou haſt reuealed mercy in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thou haſt aſſured con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation by correction. Why ſo? For I prayed vnto thée in the ſorrowes of my ſoule. <hi>Correct mee O Lord yet in thy judgement, not in thy fury,</hi> &amp;c. So I prayed, for I was content to beare thy pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, becauſe I had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt thée. This my prayer thou haſt graciouſly granted vnto me, thou hadſt reſpect vnto the humble ſuite of a ſinner. Therefore in thy fury thou didſt not correct me with violent fire which doth
<pb facs="tcp:274:51"/> deuoure the Aduerſary, with euerlaſting paines thou didſt not reward mee as I deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: but in iudgement thou haſt puniſhed me, with the corrections of men: Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, pouerty, ſickneſſe, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; and ſuch like, and ſo thou haſt graunted my petition, thou Lord haſt receiued my prayer, thou haſt chaſtned me with thy Children, leaſt I ſhould be condemned with the reprobate. And thus to me thou haſt reuealed mercy in iudgement. Thus thou haſt aſſured conſolation by correction. Héere is thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy (oh mercifull God) to graunt mee my requeſt this
<pb facs="tcp:274:52"/> was thy mercie to giue eare in this thing vnto a ſinner, this was thy great mercie, I grant it, I confeſſe it, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it, I praiſe thy name for it: Oh Iehoua. This is the garment of gladneſſe for the ſpirit of heauineſſe, oh God my heart is ready, my heart is ready, I will ſing &amp; giue prayſe. Awake my glorie, awake my grace, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake my ſoule, all the ſecrets of my Soule awake. I my ſelfe will awake right early. Reioyce (my deere Soule) in the Lord thy God, and againe I ſay reioyce. Oh righteous Father: thou haſt executed thy iuſtice, and extended thy
<pb facs="tcp:274:52"/> mercy vpon me both together. Who can declare thy noble Acts, and ſhew forth all thy prayſe? who can doe as thou doſt? can a Man? can a Saint? can an Angell? can any powre, and Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, any throne, or dominion bring good out of euill, ſwéet out of ſowre, honor out of ſhame, life out of death, out of vengeance mercy, as thou doſt? To thée therefore (oh Iehoua) and to thée alone ſhall all fleſh come, ſhall all creatures in heauen, and in earth, and vnder the earth be ſubiect, to thée ſhall my ſoule and all the ſecrets of the ſame be dutifull, and obedient from
<pb facs="tcp:274:53"/> henceforth and for euermore. I will ſing vnto thée among much people, and will not be aſhamed. I will ſpeake of thy praiſes in the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, my Soule ſhall make her boaſt of thée, and I will euer remember this, that in wrath thou thinkeſt vppon mercy. I will remember and not forget: euen ſo be it (oh Father of heauen) through Ieſus Chriſt thy onely Son, in whom thou art well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, my onely Sauiour in whome I am fully comforted. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:274:53"/>
               <head>¶ A Meditation ſealing E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Election by the conſideration of good Education.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt gracious God, and louing Father, who in thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſt before the world was made diddeſt predeſtinate, &amp; foreappoint ſome men to life, and ſome to death, ſome to glory, and ſome to contempt, ſome to ſaluation, and ſome to condemnation, euen of thy good pleaſure. I giue thée moſt humble, and hearty
<pb facs="tcp:274:54"/> thankes that thou haſt choſen me to life, glory, and ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fréely, and of thine owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, when it might haue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thée to reprobate mee for euer. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo (Father) becauſe it was thy good pleaſure: a taſt of this loue and fauour thou haſt giuen me by the reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ieſus Chriſt. Hereby I am aſſured y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate vnto eternall life, that I haue faith in the death &amp; blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of Ieſus Chriſt. O Lord encreaſe my Faith. Moreouer this thine ancient loue, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and without beginning is manifeſted to me more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, for that it pleaſed thée y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhould not only be borne of
<pb facs="tcp:274:54"/> godly parents embracing thy truth, but alſo by them bee brought vp and trained from my child-hoode in a courſe of godlineſſe and vertue, that ſo comming vnto riper yeares I might bee grounded &amp; eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in thy holy waies. Oh mercifull father, my conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and ſinnes doe teſtifie againſt me that I haue not deſerued the leaſt of thy mercies that thou haſt enriched me withall from my youth vp, much leſſe this ſo great and ineſtimable a grace to bee followed with thy louing kindneſſe, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended vppon by thy grace through good education all my life long to this preſent houre.
<pb facs="tcp:274:55"/> For (to confeſſe a truth) I haue not ceaſed to prouoke thée continually, I haue not ceaſed to tranſgreſſe againſt thy holy Maieſty, in thought, word, and déed euery day, yea Lord in great and grieuous ſort, early and late, in child-hood, in youth, in middle age, ignorantly, and wittingly, weakly and preſumptuouſly, in ſuch ſort (O Father) that it is maruaile I am not alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy conſumed, already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. Yet for all this, thy louing fauour hath accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied me euermore; and now I perceiue the good fruit of godly education. Oh my God what ſhal I render vnto thée?
<pb facs="tcp:274:55"/> how ſhall I bee thankefull? what recompence doſt thou looke for? behold I will thanke thée in Chriſt Ieſus thy belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Sonne, and my bleſſed Sauiour: I will truſt in thy mercie for euer through him. I will liue in thy feare by his power, I will ſerue thée with an vnfeigned heart, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thée in my body, and in my ſoule, by the working of his grace and ſpirit all the daies of my life. Oh conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue forth thy louing kindnes towards me from henceforth, and for euer, that being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted and guided through this vale of miſery; after I haue a little recouered my
<pb facs="tcp:274:56"/> ſtrength in bodie and ſpirit, performed my duty, patiently ſuffred, and endured the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed croſſe for me: I may in the end receiue the end of my faith and hope: euen the ſaluation of my ſoule, and at that great day the glorificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both body and ſoule through the ſame, my Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, to whome with thée, and the holy Ghoſt, be eternall and equall praiſe for euer. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:274:56"/>
               <head>¶ In weeping, mourning, and bitter anguiſh, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H Lord God, what ſhal I ſay vnto thée? O fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Heauen how ſhall I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat thée? I am horriblie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of thy iudgments, I am wonderfully abaſhed at thy glorious preſence, I am vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſhamed of mine own baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vileneſſe, wretchedneſſe, duſt, &amp; aſhes: fleſh and blood, filth and froth, ſwill, and ſinne that I am, who ſhall giue me
<pb facs="tcp:274:57"/> acceſſe and entrance before thy Maieſtie? who ſhall helpe me to entreat for thy mercy? The blood of thy Son I haue polluted and profaned, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit of grace I haue refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and deſpighted. I confeſſe my wickedneſſe, and I am ſorie for my ſinne. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof is grieuous vnto me, the burthen thereof is intollerable. Albeit my due deſert is hell, death, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: Yea, and perpetuall vexation and terrour of heart, vntill the ſentence of deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and eternall confuſion be executed vpon me, a ſpirit of vnquietneſſe to trouble mee (like the ſpirit of <hi>Saul</hi>) from
<pb facs="tcp:274:57"/> henceforth euen for euer: Yet I will hope in the multitude of thine vnſpeakable mercies vouchſafed to all ſinners in their déepeſt diſtreſſe and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie. In moſt humble wiſe as it becommeth an inferiour vaſſall to his puiſſant and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty prince and leige Lord; as it becommeth a Malefactor to an vpright and moſt wiſe Iudge, as it becommeth a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; ſtubborne ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant to his carefull Maiſter, and finally a prodigall and wilfull Child to his moſt kind and louing Father: I ſubmit my ſelfe wholly diſtaſted of mine owne deſerts, and vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deteſting mine owne abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable
<pb facs="tcp:274:58"/> conceits, words, and workes againſt thy holy will, and commandement, in the wound of conſcience, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the depth of a mind throughly grieued with my rebellions I moſt ſubmiſſely and earneſtly call and cry vnto thy moſt gracious Maieſty and mercy, for pardon and forgiuenes of my hainous crimes and innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable tranſgreſſions, in all humility and tribulation of ſpirit, beſeeching thy fatherly goodnes to lay them vpon the backe of thy deare ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that All-ſufficient Redéemer, Reconciler, and Sauiour of all thoſe that put their truſt in his moſt abſolute
<pb facs="tcp:274:58"/> merits, and perfect obedience. O my God: my ſure truſt is in him, that he will be pleaſed to accept me for one of thoſe whome he calleth in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, labouring and heauie la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with their ſinnes to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued, and eaſed; Not for any other reaſon, but becauſe hee is the right hand of thy mercy, reached out vnto fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and languiſhing ſinners, whereof I am one. Wherfore (oh deare Father of Heauen) deſpize me not approaching to the throne of grace in his only name, but let me be poſſeſſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſpirit of aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of faith ſprinckled in my heart, from an euil conſcience, that I may
<pb facs="tcp:274:59"/> find grace to helpe me now in this time of néed. I doe féele certainly, I do find the gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Worme eating vp my heart, the venome of thine ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes drinking vp my ſpirit, the rigour of thy iudgements perplexing my thoughts, the ſeuerity of thy puniſhment aſtoniſhing and amazing my weake and féeble wits, ſo that I know not, either what courſe to take to eaſe my ſelfe, either what words to vſe to entreat thy mercie. O Lord God, great and fearfull, bee not as a Lyon vnto mee, doe not ſet me as a marke to ſhoot at, for thou neuer faileſt to hit where thou aymeſt, thou
<pb facs="tcp:274:59"/> hitteſt full and home, thy ſhot is of an Archer of perfect ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, thy ſtrokes are dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrokes, thine arrowes are venomed with the fire of wrath that burneth for euer. Who is able to abide? wilt thou ſtill hold my ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my face? wilt thou ſtill encreaſe the ſorrowes of my heart? Alas what is my ſtrength? What is my faith that thou tryeſt me? Surely thou canſt find nothing in me; but exceeding weakneſſe, a daunted Spirit, a diſpairing ſoule. The thought of all my ſinnes ſince my youth vp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now ſet in order before me, doth quench the light of
<pb facs="tcp:274:60"/> the aſſured faith which I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped was within mee. O good Father prooue mee but this once, and withdraw thy pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment from me. Let not this fit of thy laſting indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion make an end of mee. I know aſſuredly thou haſt, and daily doſt forgiue ſinne, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more hainous ſinne then mine. For in the very depth of my diſobedience I haue alwaies reſtrained the vnbridled affection, and ſurely thou haſt neuer ſuffered me to this houre to giue my full and whole conſent to any ſinne whereinto I haue fallen ſince I was borne. In conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof (ſithence I haue
<pb facs="tcp:274:60"/> the ſure teſtimony of a good conſcience, that I am one of thy choſen) I humbly entreat thy Maieſty to encline thine eare to my ſupplication, and to deale with mée, as with a ſonne remembring himſelfe, and returning vnto thée in wéeping, &amp; great mourning. Let the griefe of my heart, and the teares of mine eies be accepted for all that I can do, and lay all the burden of my tranſgreſſions: late, and long ſince paſt, vpon the backe of my bleſſed Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, who for ſuch as I am dyed, and ſuffered the bitter cup of thy wrath. O be thou pacified, and well pleaſed
<pb facs="tcp:274:61"/> in him, who ſuffered the Iuſt for the vniuſt, and endured cauſeles, and vndeſeruedly all extremities, to the end thou (O righteous father) ſhouldſt be pacified and well pleaſed, with all penitent &amp; belieuing ſinners, notwithſtanding the multitude, magnitude, and turpitude of their tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Were mine abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions now to be committed, though I might conceale the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the world, I would not performe them in the preſence of thy Maieſty, becauſe thou art a God of pure eyes, and canſt not behold iniquity. I feare thee. I loue thée. I doe reuerence before thée. I adore
<pb facs="tcp:274:61"/> thy purity, integrity, thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. I am deſirous to bée like vnto thée, O thou that dwelleſt in the heauens. My ſoule hath deſire and a long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to pleaſe thee, &amp; perſeuere in thy waies, and to be renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in righteouſnes, and true holines, after thy bleſſed I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. When my ſinnes are forgiuen, and my tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wiped out of the ſcore of thy iudgements; then ſhall mercy embrace mee, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindneſſe compaſſe mée, euery morning, then ſhall my faith worke by thy loue, ſhed abroad in my heart through the holy Ghoſt, then ſhall my wonted ſtrength, and much
<pb facs="tcp:274:62"/> more alſo poſſeſſe, &amp; enarme my ſoule againſt all my dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foes, then ſhall I be clenſed and made fit for euery good worke. So ſhall the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of my heart bée reſtored vnto mée againe, and I will ſerue thée in Spirit and truth all the daies of my life. And doe render vnto thée in the meane time, nothing doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of thy frée pardon, all honour, glory, praiſe, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; thanks, now and for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:274:62"/>
               <head>¶ A <hi>De-profundis</hi> full of hope, and godly reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H Lord my God the comforter of all the choſen, from whoſe only throne procéedeth ioy &amp; glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, peace and comfort, and euerlaſting felicitie, in whoſe preſence is the fulneſſe of ioy, at whoſe right hand there are pleaſures for euermore, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whoſe chéerefull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and pleaſant aſpect no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is amiable, no Soule is ioyfull; vouchſafe to ſhine
<pb facs="tcp:274:63"/> into my woefull heart, euen pined &amp; confumed with griefe, through my dayly complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: miſerably rent, and torne in péeces through conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall mourning day &amp; night, perplexed and diſtracted vnto the very death through perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall tribulation, and anguiſh without ceaſing. I know that one fauourable aſpect of thy grace vpon me can reſtore me to vnſpeakable gladneſſe. Oh that it were thy pleaſure to afford it me, to bring mée backe from the graue, which I behold as it were already opened for my tranſgreſſions. In truth my griefe is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of me; yet it doth aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb facs="tcp:274:63"/> me. I find my ſelfe in farre worſe caſe then euer in my life, neuer was I pierced ſo much at the heart roote. I haue not heretofore receiued ſo déepe, and deſperate, and deadly wound in my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. If thou (Lord) vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to rid me out of this thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and euen helliſh capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity, being faſt bound in the chaines of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable thoughts, O my Lord, my good God, my heart &amp; tongue ſhall ſing for euer vnto thy prayſe. I will publiſh thy mercies, I will teach thy iudgements vnto thy people. I will praiſe thée in the great congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I will wholy conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate
<pb facs="tcp:274:64"/> and deuote my ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée all the daies of my life. Oh Father of heauen giue &amp; beſtow fréely vppon mée the moſt excellent gift of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained Faith, that my ſinnes are forgiuen me for thy déere ſonne Ieſus Chriſts ſake: let me fully be aſſured thereof by the Spirit the comforter. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déed it doth not belong vnto mée I confeſſe, I confeſſe, I will not deny. For I haue behaued my ſelfe more like a reprobate, and damned crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture then one of thy children. Surely ſuch Carrion curs as I am, that trample the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, and deſpiſe the ſpirit of grace ſo ſinfully,
<pb facs="tcp:274:64"/> ſo ſhamefully, ſo often, ſo odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, ſo preſumptuouſly, ſo intollerably, as I haue done, are not worthy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt crum of thy mercifull comfort: yet Lord, ſith I am but duſt and aſhes, and through the frailty of the old Adam, I haue thus abuſed thy goodnes, refuſing and vexing thy holy ſpirit, for which damnable inſolency, I am now moſt wofully diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racted, and almoſt bereft of my ſmall wits; the déepe thoughts whereof doe ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly aſſault mee; O my Father, and my God: contend not with me any longer; I ſhal ſurely deſpaire, and bée damned, if thou ſend me not
<pb facs="tcp:274:65"/> ayd and peace of Conſcience ſpéedily; How can I lye in theſe ſcorching flames? Oh conſider mine exceding weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Oh good Samaritane: powre wine and oyle into my bléeding wounds. Oh ſwéet Ieſu let me not be caſt away, becauſe I haue put my truſt in thée. I will not let thée go vntill thou bleſſe me. (Now bleſſed Sauiour) many of my prayers haue béene refuſed let this be accepted; ſith thou haſt giuen me a time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, with moſt humble tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks giue me leaue to accept it. Caſt me not out of thy preſence. I deſire to be at reſt in my ſpirit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may go chéer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb facs="tcp:274:65"/> forward in the holy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. What ſhall I ſay? how ſhall I entreat? good Lord haue mercy vpon me. Oh let thy tender mercies comfort my diſtreſſed, and heale my wounded heart, one drop of thy mercy ſwéet Ieſu, ſwéet Ieſu, mercy or no mercie, all honour, and glory, and praiſe, and powre, might, and Maieſtie be aſcribed vnto thée for euer and euer <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:274:66"/>
               <head>¶ A true penitents confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and petition for grace.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> MOST migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prince &amp; Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and Earth, Lord God of hoſtes, inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; incomprehenſible Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, whoſe wiſedome is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, whoſe power vnreſiſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, whoſe mercie vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, haue mercy vppon me moſt wofull Captiue &amp; Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tife, enthralled to ſinne, to Satan, to the powers of darkneſſe, to the ſorrowes of
<pb facs="tcp:274:66"/> ſoule, to the tribulations and anguiſh of a guilty Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by my moſt heinous offences, and criminous e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normities, moſt ridiculous, and abſurd vanities, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in once I found ſome fond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light; but now I find no ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d comfort, only diſcontentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, indignation, woe, and ſhame. I am abaſhed, and confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and in a wonderfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed agony, that I ſhould ſo déepely, ſo deadly, ſo often, offend thy moſt excellent Maieſtie, who art a God of pure eyes, and canſt not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold iniquity. For albeit ſuch is the drouzie dulnes of our curſed corruption, that wée
<pb facs="tcp:274:67"/> cannot, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaucy preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our wilful inclination, that we will not ſet thée before our eyes, when we are temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſinne, and moued to tranſgreſſion: yet certaine is it, that thine eare of ielouſie heareth all things, and thine eye of ielouzie ſéeth all things and nothing is hid from the brightnes of them, ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times brighter then the Sun, but whatſoeuer worke is in our hands, whatſoeuer word in our mouthes, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thought or imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in our hearts, thou O Lord knoweſt it altogether. And as all our ways &amp; works, are all naked and open before thy
<pb facs="tcp:274:67"/> ſight; y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> loueſt righteouſnes, and hateſt iniquity, therefore when we are ſinfull, yet thou continueſt holy, excellent in glory, vpright in iuſtice, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty in power; as thou many times ſpareſt when we deſerue puniſhment; ſo thou many times woundeſt with thy iuſt reuenge when wee feele it not till afterwards, we flatter our ſelues in our own ſight, till our abhominable ſinnes be found out, till thou reprooue vs ſharply, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely ſet before vs the things that we haue done, till thou makeſt a Catalogue and roll of our offences, &amp; ſetteſt our ſecret ſinnes in order before
<pb facs="tcp:274:68"/> vs, and preſenteſt thy ſelfe withall a iuſt reuenger, our manifold breaches, of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Commandements, and manifeſt conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of thy bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ed word, of thy iuſt iudgements and of thy louing mercies, conſider not in our hearts, our moſt accurſed, and damnable eſtate wherein wee dayly plunge our ſelues moſt odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and abhominable, yea though our ſinnes be not of the ſmalleſt; but great and grieuous, and heynous and enormous abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; yet either ſuch is the groſſe dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and palpable blindnes of our minds, and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, or ſuch is the deadnes
<pb facs="tcp:274:68"/> of our infected conſciences, that wee runne on ſtill from one iniquity to another, till we ſodainly fall into thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie diſpleaſure, till thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and fiery wrath breake forth like fire vpon vs, and we be not able to quench it. Hence is it that wee are plunged into many fearefull gulfes of deſperation. Wée are affrighted with many vg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſights of our ſinnes, hence we are wounded at the very heart with many diſtruſtfull thoughts of thy mercies, and as many deſperate imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thy vengeance The paines of hell get hold vpon vs, and the feare of thée doth
<pb facs="tcp:274:69"/> vndoe vs, before either wée ſtand in awe of thy Maieſty, or ſéeke after thy mercy; Oh my God and Sauiour I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe vnfainedly this my caſe: ſo I haue tranſgreſſed, ſo little I haue regarded, ſo I am op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed; Wherefore O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercies, and God of all conſolation, who haſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted repentance for ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, who dwelleſt in eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and yet in the humble and contrite ſpirit: In the name of thy holy, and bleſſed, and onely beloued ſonne our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, who hath promiſed eaſe to all that labouring and heauy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, come vnto him: who
<pb facs="tcp:274:69"/> 
                  <hi>cannot breake the bruized Reed, and will not quench the ſmoaking flaxe,</hi> I moſt humbly and earneſtly beſéech and entreat thy fatherly good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to forgiue me all my ſins, to lay them vpon his backe, the true ſcape-goat, and ſend them into the wildernes, the land of obliuion, that my Conſcience through faith in his moſt precious bloud and meritorious ſacrifice may bée fully diſcharged of them all. O Prince of peace, ſend peace into my heart: the peace that paſſeth vnderſtanding, that peace which thou gaueſt for a Legacy to thy Diſciples, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before thy death thou diddeſt
<pb facs="tcp:274:70"/> make promiſe of that ſpirit the Comforter. O holie ſpirit of Comfort, the onely ioye of thine elect, let thy bleſſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ſo chéere and glad my ſoule, that being aſſured of thy ſauing health, I may delight to ſerue thée, and to ſanctifie my ſelfe more and more with all allacrity and pleaſure of my ſpirit attending on thy will, &amp; walking in thy wayes all the reſidue of this my pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, &amp; mortalitie. Grant this O Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, holie, bleſſed, and eternall Trinity, the Author of Life, the giuer of grace, the God of power, whoſe wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is péereleſſe, whoſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion
<pb facs="tcp:274:70"/> is endles, whoſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is bottomleſſe: To whom be all praiſe, honour, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for euer, and euer, world without end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A ſpeciall forme of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and ſupplication to the Almighty.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T cannot bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied (oh Lord GOD almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) it is too well knowne to thée, and too too la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentably experienced in our ſelues, that we are nothing elſe but a ſinke, and ſwill, and puddle of ſinne, a maſſe and
<pb facs="tcp:274:71"/> lumpe of rebellion. That there is no light in our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, no good inclination in our good will, no grace in our life: we haue erred, and ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from thy waies euer ſince we were borne, through the originall Concupiſcence and Corruption wherein wee are conceiued, we haue neuer cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to breake thy holie Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and to runne headlong into all manner of diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. When the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is ready wee are fit to bee tempted, as he is neuer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready; ſo wee alwaies are tempted, and taken in moſt dangerous and deadly gins. Woe and alas to our moſt
<pb facs="tcp:274:71"/> weake &amp; féeble ſoules, wherin there is neither power, nor will, nor wiſedome to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the fierce and violent aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the ſpiritual wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes that fight againſt vs, that entrench, and encampe themſelues round about vs; when wee thinke that all is ſafe, then ruſh they vpon vs, as the Philiſtims did vppon <hi>Sampſon,</hi> &amp; we through dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance with this wanton <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilah</hi> of our owne fleſh, and filthy vanitie of this wicked world are lulled a ſléep in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſecurity, and haue loſt our ſpirituall ſtrength of Faith, hope, and godlineſſe, and ſo are taken, and bound, and
<pb facs="tcp:274:72"/> blinded, and lead away Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, &amp; held in thraldome, and ſcorned of thoſe wicked and helliſh fiends, who greatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the deſtruction and confuſion of thy children, which thirſt and long after our eternall damnation. In tender and bitter conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof moſt lamentably complaining vnto thy moſt excellent and incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Maieſty, (oh Lord God of hoaſts) thy moſt diſtreſſed and forlorne ſeruant, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted ſonne ſheweth, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth his grieuances: and being tyred, wearied, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerburdened with moſt cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning crafts &amp; ſubtile ſleights,
<pb facs="tcp:274:72"/> as alſo moſt outragious ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannies, and impetuous vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences of his implacable, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall foes: in all humility and lowlineſſe of mind with no leſſe griefe and ſorrow of a perplexed heart, moſt ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, deuoutly, and feruently beſéecheth thy ſupereminent, &amp; far moſt excéeding excellent Highnes, to ſend out thy moſt mighty and powerfull ſpirit to ayd and aſſiſt mee in theſe aſſaults. Oh let thine Angels pitch their tents round about me to diſcomfite all thoſe that haue euill will at my ſoule. Of thy goodneſſe beate them backe that annoy me. I am ſore troubled and hindered in
<pb facs="tcp:274:73"/> that courſe of godlines where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I would walke. Oh let me runne the way of thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and ſet my heart at liberty. My ſoule hath a deſire and a longing to be pertaker of thy ſtrength: I know none ſo weak, yet none ſo deſirous to bee ſtrong in thée. Oh my God ſet me not againſt thée as a marke, my building is of the clay, my foundation is in the duſt. How can I chooſe if thou deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer me into the hand of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but fall away preſently? Ariſe (O God of my Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) and let mine enemies be put to flight, let me not be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne, becauſe I haue
<pb facs="tcp:274:73"/> hoped in thy holy name. Let no temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouercharge me, becauſe my truſt is onely in thy mighty hand, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched arme. Were it that I reſted in my ſelfe at all, or that I did not wholy renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce mine owne ſtrength, which is very féebleneſſe it ſelfe; I ſhould not dare to call vpon thée: but ſith I am wholy diſcouraged and caſt downe in my ſelfe, and indéed I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with temptations, and am heauy laden with many ſinnes, I preſume in all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble obiection, and proſtration of my ſoule and body, from a broken and a contrite ſpirit, which thou neuer vſeſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:274:74"/> to entreat thy fauour and fatherly protection, that (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his moſt gracious promiſe) I may be refreſhed and eaſed by thy bleſſed Son my onely hope and Sauiour. I doe very well know, and in all dutifull thankfulnes vpon mine owne experience I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that the holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the comforter proceeding from you both, is of All-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and inuincible force and wiſedome to withſtand, and confound all thoſe that come againſt my ſoule. Be they neuer ſo many Legions of vncleane and wicked ſpirits: yet one only comfortable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, and Inſpiration of
<pb facs="tcp:274:74"/> that your mighty and victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirit of Grace is fully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to mortifie, and kill all the venemous contagions and infections wherewith they haue empoyſoned my ſéely ſoule. Wherfore (O Father of eternall mercies) who loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt vpon the abiect and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne offenders, with a louing and compaſſionate aſpect, who art woont to be entreated of broken hearted wretches, I beſeech thée, I beſéech thée, with diſtilling teares I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, heartily, and earneſtly beſeech thee hide not thy face, withdraw not thy helping hand from me; but in tender conſideration of my excéeding
<pb facs="tcp:274:75"/> griefe, and diſtraction of mind for my ſinnes paſt, mine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant frailnes, and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable weakneſſe, to reſiſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults and temptations to come; be preſent with me thou guide and gouernour of my life, to ſmite the enemie at his approach. Enter into me O ſpirit of power, and rule with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mee mightily; Kéepe the Sconſe, the Fortreſſe, the Bulwarke, the Caſtle of my heart: vnite, and knit my will and thoughts vnto thée, and enable me with a garriſon of heauenly graces, that I may not onely defend my ſelfe; but plague them that hate and hurt my ſoule. For I am thy
<pb facs="tcp:274:75"/> ſeruant, and ſo wilbe for euer. All other fréedome is but bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and ſlauery, thy onely ſeruice is perfect fréedome, and therefore vnto that doe I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take my ſelfe. Receiue me (O Lord) and caſt me not away. I will fight in thy field, and dwell in thy houſe all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daies of my life, becauſe to feare thée, and loue thée, and liue after thy will is my whole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and perfect ioy. And glory be vnto thée, O God moſt high; euen all glory, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and praiſe, now and for euermore. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:274:76"/>
               <head>¶ A petition for a feeling Conſcience.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am now deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and fully reſolued, Lord God eternall, moſt gracious and mercifull Father, to giue an euerlaſting farewell to all mine impious and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous deſignes. Haue mercy vpon me, haue mercy vpon me: ayd and aſſiſt me with thy conſtant Spirit. There is no beginning, there is no ending, there is no procéeding in a godly courſe without thy
<pb facs="tcp:274:76"/> ſpeciall helpe. Satan by the world and originall corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is able to ouerthrow the ſtrongeſt ſoule. But the ſtrength of one of thine An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels is farre beyond all power of Satan. How much more the powerfull inſpiration of the ſpirit of grace? Now Lord, I am perſwaded by the ſame that I am fully reconciled vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée: that my many and mighty ſinnes are vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced, and raſed out of the Booke of the memoriall of thy moſt iuſt iudgements. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in aſſured confidence of thy manifold mercies, and full aſſuranre of thy louing fauor; in all humility and lowlines
<pb facs="tcp:274:77"/> of heart I ſubmit my ſelfe to thy moſt mighty Maieſty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéeching the ſame to look vpon my miſery, whereinto I haue plunged my ſelfe by my follie; and put the moſt holy ſpirit of Comfort, Chriſtian courage, and Conſtancy vpon me: And let it rule within me to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowing of the kingdome of Sinne and Satan in my Heart and Conſcience, in my Life and Conuerſation conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually. It is well knowne vnto thée, and I doe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that ſuch, and ſo great are, and haue béene, mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normities from time to time, that they are able to breake the ſtouteſt heart; the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance</p>
               <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
